Guide to the Francis Warrington Dawson Family Papers, 1386-1963 (bulk 1859-1950)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Francis Warrington Dawson Family papers 1386-1963 (bulk 1859-1950)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Dawson, Francis Warrington, 1840-1889.
10.5 linear feet Extent: 7986 Items
Journalist, of Charleston, S.C., and Versailles, France. The collection (7918 items; dated 1386-1963, bulk 1859-1950) contains the papers of Francis Warrington Dawson, who was born Austin John Reeks; his wife, Sarah Ida Fowler Morgan Dawson; and their son, Francis Warrington Dawson II, better known as Warrington Dawson. The papers are primarily literary in character but also include many letters. Francis's papers are primarily autobiographical with information about his Civil War service, travels, courtship, and career. Also present are Morgan family papers describing social life in New Orleans and Baton Rouge, La., in the second half of the 19th century, especially during Reconstruction. Warrington Dawson materials document his work with the American Embassy in Paris and describes French life and politics. Also present is material from his work as director of French Research for Colonial Williamsburg, Inc., including copies (made from the originals at Colonial Williamsburg) of original documents pertaining to French participation in the American Revolution. Also included are copies of 18th century maps of North America, Williamsburg, Va., and positions of the French and American armies in New York and Virginia during the Revolutionary War.
dawsonfrancisw
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Francis Warrington Dawson Family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift between 1950-1988.
Collection Overview
The collection comprises the papers of Francis Warrington (Frank) Dawson (1840-1889), whose original name was Austin John Reeks; his wife, Sarah Ida Fowler (Morgan) Dawson; and of their son, Francis Warrington Dawson II, known as Warrington Dawson (1878-1962). The papers are primarily literary in character, with many editorials, newspaper writings, short stories, novels, articles, and scrapbooks, diaries, and reminiscences, but also many letters. Papers of the senior Dawson contain three scrapbooks of clippings, letters, etc., which Dawson had arranged as a sort of biography of himself; loose letters and papers, primarily correspondence with his wife; two letterpress volumes with his replies to many of the letters in the scrapbooks and in the loose papers. Morgan family correspondence, beginning in 1859, describes the social life and customs in Baton Rouge and New Orleans, Louisiana; in Paris, France; and the death of Henry Waller Morgan in a duel in 1861. Letters of Thomas Gibbes Morgan, Sr., describe Confederate mobilization in 1861. Correspondence of Frank Dawson and members of the Morgan family describe Dawson's passage on the blockade runner Nashville, his career as ordnance officer in Longstreet's corps and later in Fitzhugh Lee's cavalry corps; the destruction of homes in Louisiana by the war and Butler's conduct in New Orleans; the battle of Fredericksburg; imprisonment at Fort Delaware; refugee life at Macon, Mississippi; cavalry operations; the causes of Confederate defeat; a duel of Henry Rives Pollard, editor of the Richmond Examiner; politics and journalism in Reconstruction South Carolina; the editorial policies of Dawson's paper, the Charleston News and Courier; accusations of bribery, fraud, and libel; the courtship of Dawson and Sarah (Morgan) Dawson; Dawson's refusal of a challenge to a duel by Martin Witherspoon Gary; the army bill, 1879; the Tilden-Hayes disputed election, 1876; the redemption of South Carolina; Morgan family genealogy; travel in Italy and Europe in the 1880s; education in South Carolina at state-supported colleges and the Citadel; the Charleston earthquake, 1886; Dawson's alleged remarks about Grover Cleveland, reported in the New York World, 1886; labor and labor organizations; the tariff; court procedures in South Carolina; Confederate veterans' organizations; Democratic Party affairs; Dawson's debts; his murder; and the settlement of his estate. Among Dawson's frequent correspondents are Daniel Henry Chamberlain, Edward B. Dickinson, Samuel Dibble, Fitzhugh Lee, Robert Baker Pegram, Henry A. M. Smith, Hugh Smith Thompson, Benjamin Ryan Tillman, Giddings Whitney, and Benjamin H. Wilson.
There is also correspondence of Sarah Dawson and Warrington Dawson, newsman, novelist, editor, special assistant to the American Embassy in Paris, and director of French research for Colonial Williamsburg. This material gives glimpses of French life, 1900-1950, and information on the families of Joseph Conrad and Theodore Roosevelt. Regular letters of Sarah Dawson to Eunice (Martin) Dunkin (Mrs. William Huger Dunkin) and to her sister, Mrs. Lavina (Morgan) Drum of Bethesda, Maryland, comment on French and Washington, D.C., social life and customs. Dawson's writings as Paris correspondent of the United Press Associations of America after 1900 are in clippings in the scrapbooks. They reflect French and world affairs. Topics treated in correspondence include Theodore Roosevelt's safari; Roosevelt's opinions; press relations for the Roosevelt party in Africa; Roosevelt's reviews of Dawson's books; Dawson's lectures and writings; Conrad's writings; other literary matters; John Powell's career as a concert pianist; seances and mediums; the Taft administration; Roosevelt and race relations; the Negro in Liberia, Nigeria, Haiti, and the U.S.; Roosevelt's political career; the Fresh Air Art Society of London; the organization of the press bureau in the U.S. embassy in Paris; and the work of the Foreign Department of the Committee on Public Information.
Embassy memoranda by Dawson cover the Central Powers; the Supreme War Council meetings; French labor; the liberated regions of France; the Young Men's Christian Association; reaction to U.S. requisition of Dutch shipping; the Rhine frontier; allied land transportation; French government bureaus, personnel, politics, and administration; economic affairs; and finance in the Far East. Postwar diplomatic memoranda by Dawson, 1946-1958, 3 vols., concern French economic conditions, labor, communism, atomic warfare, politics, French leaders including Charles de Gaulle, Indochina, and the U.S.S.R. Letters also cover German reparations; relief work in Austria and the Near East; details of embassy staff work; George Harvey's mission to Europe, 1921; the Washington Disarmament Conference; French finance and politics; war debts; international finance; Coueism; French socialism; a crisis in the publication of the Charleston News and Courier, 1927; the boy scout movement; the Conrad family after Joseph's death; Theodore Roosevelt; U.S. investment in the U.S.S.R.; the restoration of Colonial Williamsburg, Virginia; the French dead at Yorktown; research in French sources on Rochambeau's army; reports to Harold Shurtleff, in charge of the research department of Colonial Williamsburg; the research of Peter Stuyvesant Barry on his grandfather, Frank Dawson; personal and family matters; Dawson's health; restoration of the Lee mansion, Stratford; the Great Depression in the United States and in France; the genealogy of the Chambrun family; the role of Lafayette in Florida land settlement; the Compañía Arrendataria del Monopolio de Petroleos, a Spanish firm in which the French Petroleum Company held an interest; the war records of Theodore Roosevelt's sons; and autograph collecting for the Schroeder Foundation, Webster Groves, Missouri. Major correspondents of Warrington Dawson include Ethel (Dawson) Barry, Phyllis (Windsor-Clive) Benton, Jessie Conrad, Joseph Conrad, Annie Cothran, Alice Dukes, Camille Flammarion, Clarence Payne Franklin, A. H. Frazier, Hugh Gibson, Alice Stopford Green, Yves Guyot, Mary Goodwin, William Archer Rutherfoord Godwin, Herman Hagedorn, Ralph Tracy Hale, Constance (Cary) Harrison, Leland Harrison, Elizabeth Hayes, Henriette Joffre, James Kerney, Grace King, Rudyard Kipling, Georges Ladoux, William Loeb, Jr., Samuel Frank Logan, Andrew W. Miller, C. V. Miller, Francois Millet, L. D. Morel, James Morris Morgan, Frederick Palmer, John Powell, Auguste Rodin, the Duke end Duchess de Rohan, Edith Roosevelt, Nicholas Roosevelt, Theodore Roosevelt, Max Savelle, H. L. Schroeder, George Sharp, Hallie (Clough) Sharp, Philip Simms, George E. Smith, Vance Thompson, and Robert William Vail.
A group of transcripts of diplomatic dispatches of Comte Louis Barbe Charles Serurier, French minister in Washington, to Talleyrand, Oct., 1812-June, 1813, describe the opening phrases of the War of 1812, United States opinion concerning France, the divorce proceedings of Elizabeth (Patterson) Bonaparte, interviews with Secretary of State James Monroe, Joel Barlow's negotiations for a commercial treaty with France, embargo, non-importation, and impressment; Republican and Federalist activities; and affairs in New Granada (Columbia). A later series of dispatches from the French minister in Washington, Alphonse J. Y. Pageot, 1835-1848, relates to American spoliation claims against France, American public opinion, analyses of nullification, the Bank of the United States crisis, abolition, and other aspects of American politics. Dispatches of 1841-1843 from Madrid contain information on Spanish affairs, and the guardianship and marriage of the Spanish queen. Later dispatches from Washington concern commercial relations between France and the United States; annexation of Texas and Oregon; the Mexican War and the question of slavery in the territories and its implications for disunion; and the war's effect on French commerce.
Among bills, receipts, and legal papers are materials of J. M. Morgan and the DeSaussure-Trenholm family, financial papers of the Charleston News and Courier, and records of the settlement of the estate of Frank Dawson.
There are manuscripts of writings by Sarah Dawson; manuscripts, fragments, lectures by Warrington Dawson and Theodore Roosevelt; a log and a diary of Roosevelt's African trip; Roosevelt's notes on the policy of his administration in regard to Negroes; extracts from letters and speeches which the former president supplied for use in connection with Dawson's book, Opportunity and Theodore Roosevelt; manuscripts of the book; essays and drafts by Jessie Conrad, Auguste Rodin, Vance Thompson, and Georges Ladoux, reflecting on Dawson's friendships and literary collaborations; and other manuscripts dealing with psychical research. There are also manuscripts, research instructions, notes, page proofs, and other papers resulting from Dawson's research for Colonial Williamsburg, and from his novels and short stories; genealogical papers of the Morgan family and related Gibbes, Fowler, Waller, Hunt, Bunyan, and Baynton families, including a chart of the Reeks family of England; and notes for Dawson's lectures on art, France, Charleston, the Negro in America, Joseph Conrad, and Theodore Roosevelt.
Bound volumes include Frank Dawson's scrapbooks, 1875-1888, 3 vols., relating to his editorship of the Charleston News and Courier and to Democratic politics, and contain editorials, and other newspaper clippings relating to Dawson, letters from his friends, and speeches. There is information on Dawson's opinions concerning the economic theories of Henry George and letters from George. There are also letterpress books, 2 vols., 1870s-1887, largely containing political correspondence. Miscellaneous volumes hold Dawson's plays, poems, clippings, and copies of letters from Mary Haxall. Business records include an address book; cashbook, 1886-1888; ledger, 1867-1872; notebook on the finances of the News and Courier; a private ledger, 1867-1887; and miscellaneous financial notebooks. For Sarah Dawson there are scrapbooks, 1853-1882, 3 vols., with clippings, her letters to the News and Courier, and accounts of the death of Frank Dawson and tributes to him. Sarah Dawson's manuscript diaries, 1862-1866, 6 vols. (largely published 1913), also include notes from ca. 1896-1906. There are notebooks of Sarah explaining her husband's death, a manuscript by Warrington Dawson commenting on the same subject, and biographical accounts of Frank Dawson and other family members. Other notebooks of Sarah Dawson, 4 vols., 1898-1908, concern her life, travel, and psychical phenomena.
There are diaries of Warrington Dawson, 1898, 1914-1918, 1930-1931, 1934-1945, 4 vols., and of Ethel Dawson, 1888-1891, 1 vol. Warrington's reminiscences of World War I deal with the French intelligence service and attributes the origin of his illness and that of Woodrow Wilson to German biological warfare. A second reminiscence concerns his work for the American Embassy in the 1930s and his life in Paris under German occupation, and has information on the dietary work of B. Lytton-Bernard (Bernard Trappachuh). A third reminiscence gives a mystical interpretation of world events, 1932-1945. Warrington Dawson also left scrapbooks, 1884-1952, 4 vols., preserving many of his newspaper writings. Dawson's collection of French manuscripts and autographs, 1386-1830, relates to his interest in genealogy and concern the de Bethune, de Crequi, Chevalier, and related families, and include a few parchments concerning Maximilien de Béthune, Duc de Sully, and Henry IV, King of France.
The collection includes a number of photographs of Joseph and Jessie Conrad, Warrington Dawson, Sarah Dawson, Ethel (Dawson) Barry, Herbert Barry, Frank Dawson, Daniel H. Chamberlain (Reconstruction governor of South Carolina), François Millet, Woodrow Wilson, Archibald Forbes, Lord Windsor, the Chateau de Josselin (signed by the Duke and Duchess de Rohan), historical monuments and their inscriptions in Virginia, the Charleston earthquake, and Warrington Dawson's Versailles apartment.
There is also microfilm, 1 reel, of published and unpublished works by and about Warrington Dawson and Joseph Conrad, filmed from the originals at the Ralph Foster Museum, The School of the Ozarks, Point Lookout, Missouri.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Dawson, Francis Warrington, 1840-1889; Dawson, Sarah Morgan, 1842-1909; Morgan, Howell; Dawson, Warrington, 1878-1962; Morgan family; Colonial Williamsburg Foundation -- Employees; Dramatists; Journalists -- Correspondence; Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877)--Louisiana; Diplomatic and consular service, American -- France; New York (State)--Maps; Baton Rouge (La.)--Social life and customs; France -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Louisiana -- Social life and customs; New Orleans (La.)--Social life and customs; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives, Confederate; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Participation, French; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Sources; Williamsburg (Va.)--Maps; North America -- Maps; Virginia -- Maps; Maps; Conrad, Joseph, 1857-1924; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Charleston News and Courier; Charleston earthquake, S.C., 1886 -- Pictorial works
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1859-1963 and undated, (31 boxes); Material in this series has been first arranged according to the creator's surname (the majority also include the recipient's name), and then by date. Unsigned or unidentified correspondence can be found in "General Corresondence" folders at the end of each box, organized by date. The finding aid lists the dates of each box and includes creators found within that box.
  - Correspondence, 1859-1873 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1874-1885 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1886-1887 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1888-1889, Jan.-Mar. 14 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1889, Mar. 15-1899 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1900-1907 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1908-1910 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1911-1917 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1918-1920 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1921 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1922-1924 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1926 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1927-1928 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1929 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1930, Jan.-Sept. (Box 15)
  - Correspondence, 1930, Oct.-Dec. (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1931, Jan.-Mar. (Box 17)
  - Correspondence, 1931, Apr.-June (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, 1931, July-Sept. (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, 1931, Oct.-Nov. (Box 20)
  - Correspondence, 1931, Dec.-1932, Feb. (Box 21)
  - Correspondence, 1932, Mar.-July (Box 22)
  - Correspondence, 1932, Aug.-Dec. (Box 23)
  - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 24)
  - Correspondence, 1934-1935 (Box 25)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1939 (Box 26)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1963 (Box 27)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 28)
  - Diplomatic correspondence, 1946-1958 (Box 29)
  - Memos to the United States Embassy in Paris, Vols. I, II, and III (typescript)
  - Diplomatic correspondence, 1812-1848 (Box 30)
  - Dispatches of Louis Serurier and Alphonse Pageot
  - Bills and receipts (Box 31)
  - Legal papers
- Writings, (38 boxes)
  - Extracts made by Sarah (Morgan) Dawson from the correspondence of Madame, Duchesse d'Orleans, Charlotte Elizabeth of Bavaria, mother of the Regent of France, Vols. I and II (Box 32)
  - Sarah (Morgan) Dawson (Box 33)
    - Memoirs of Manquise de Crequy
    - Miscellaneous writings
  - Joseph Conrad and F.W. Dawson II, on Joseph Conrad (Box 34)
  - Auguste Rodin and Vance Thompson
  - Theodore Roosevelt (including F.W. Dawson II writings and Opportunity and Theodore Roosevelt) (Box 35)
  - Theodore Roosevelt (Box 36)
    - British East Africa Log
    - Scribble Diary
    - Roosevelt speeches
    - Roosevelt on Race. Pictures.
  - Revolutionary War Papers (Box 37)
    - Photostats and copies of correspondence of Comte de Rochambeau, George Washington, Benjamin Franklin, et al.
    - French Officers: dossiers, journals, souvenirs and letters (A-G) (Box 38)
    - French Officers: dossiers, journals, souvenirs, and letters (L-Z) (Box 39)
    - Maps, research memoranda, new series, press releases, nos. 1-200, Feb. 24-Sept. 5, 1931 (Box 40)
    - Research memoranda, new series nos. 201-445, Sept. 7, 1931-Aug. 5, 1932 (Box 41)
    - Page proof of Dawson book on French dead (Box 42)
    - Lists of French dead in America
    - Lists of French regiments, of maps, research institutions, etc.
    - Miscellaneous Segonne research memoranda duplicates (Box 43)
  - Early prose and poetry, 1890s (Box 44)
  - Poems (1 vol.)
  - Vengeance Cast Away
  - The Arrow of Love
  - Blink's Ghost
  - The Mistaken Engagement; Volatile Gratitude
  - Georges Ladoux and F.W. Dawson III (Box 45)
  - Marthe Richard and The Kaiser's Blonde Spy
  - The True Dimension (from the mss. The Purser's Shilling) (Box 46)
  - The Gift of Paul Clermont (3 vols.) (Box 47)
  - Paul Clermont's Story and My Own (Box 48)
  - LeDon de Paul Clermont
  - The Scar (holo. mss.) (Box 49)
  - The Scar (typescript and fragment) (Box 50)
  - The Scourge (typescript and fragment)
  - The Scourge (holo. mss.) (Box 51)
  - The Grand Elixir (The Green Mustache) (Box 52)
  - Adventure in the Night (Box 53)
  - The Guardian Demons (Box 54)
  - Sibylla
  - The Rock (Border Lines) (Box 55)
  - The Rock (Border Lines) (Box 56)
  - Buzz and Fury (Box 57)
  - Introduction, A Confederate Girl's Diary
  - The Pyramid (Box 58)
  - Living Art-A Novel of Paris (Box 59)
  - The Pyramid
  - Le Negre and Etats Unis (Box 60)
  - The Sin
  - The Golden Part
  - Exhit Wills (The Flight)
  - Miscellany (Box 61)
  - Reminiscences: 13 Windows, etc.
  - Texas Duel (Box 62)
  - Essential Stories
  - The Corpse and the Curtain
  - The Novel of George (Box 63)
  - The Pyramid
  - The Sin-An Allegory of Truth
  - Thad Wrenson (Box 64)
  - The Idyl of Mayna Vayne
  - The Virgin of Ivory (holo. mss.) (Box 65)
  - Le Rapt de la Vierge
  - The Man Who Wouldn't Be Dead (Box 66)
  - The Crystal Screen
  - War Memoirs and Miscellany of William Graves Sharp (1) (Box 67)
  - War Memoirs and Miscellany of William Graves Sharp (2) (Box 68)
  - War Memoirs and Miscellany of William Graves Sharp (3) (Box 69)
  - Morgan Family Biographies and Genealogies (including articles by James Morris Morgan) (Box 70)
  - Lectures and short writings by F.W. Dawson II (Box 71)
  - Pscyhic
  - Lectures and short writings by F.W. Dawson II (Box 72)
  - Dawson family biographies (Box 73)
  - Notebooks on the death of F.W. Dawson I by Sarah (Morgan) Dawson
  - Fragment of Confederate Memoirs; including the J.C. Hemphill sketch of F.W. Dawson I.
- Volumes, (10 boxes, 4 volumes)
  - Drama, poetry, and accounts (Box 74)
  - Papers and scrapbooks of F.W. Dawson I (Box 75)
  - Scrapbook I, 1875-1884
  - Letterpress books of F.W. Dawson I
    - I, 1879-1884
    - II, 1884-1887
  - Diaries and reminiscences (Box 76)
  - Think It Not Strange, World War I
  - At Neptune's Gates, World War II and later reminiscenes of 1914-1918
  - Guest Book, 1909-1929
  - Charleston Murders
  - Scrapbook, 1853-1882, of Sarah Fowler (Morgan) Dawson (Box 77)
  - Four notebooks, 1898-1908, of Sarah Fowler (Morgan) Dawson
    The notebooks contain entries concerning her girlhood; Charleston, South Carolina; foreign travel; and mediums, spiritualism, and supernatural phenomena such as the reappearance of her deceased husband.
  - Diary of Sarah Ida Fowler (Morgan) Dawson (6 vols.), 1862-1865 with postscripts, 1866-1960 (Box 78)
  - Robertson's Introduction
  - Scrapbooks, 1888-1892 and 1930-1931 (Box 79)
  - Ethel (Dawson) Barry, Diary, 1888-1891 (Box 80)
  - F.W. Dawson II, Sea Diary, 1898 (1 vol.)
  - F.W. Dawson II, War Diary, 1914-1918 (5 vols.)
  - F.W. Dawson II, Williamsburg Diary, 1930-1931 (typscript)
  - Sarah (Morgan) Dawson, Scrapbook, 1880-1897 (Box 81)
  - Sarah (Morgan) Dawson, Scrapbook, 1889-1893)
  - Scrapbooks of F.W. Dawson (3 volumes), 1878-1887 (Box 82)
  - Scrapbooks, 1884-1915 and 1910-1953 (Box 83)
  - Sarah Fowler (Morgan) Dawson's scrapbook of clippings concerning Capt. Dawson's death, 1889-1893 (Volume F:5323)
  - A Tribute to Capt. Dawson from the Merchant's Exchange of Charleston, S.C., 1889 (Box 100)
  - Book, In Memoriam, Francis Warrington Dawson, 1840-1889 (Box 100)
  - The National Democratic Committee in Memoriam (for Francis Warrington Dawson) (Box 100)
- Printed Material, (4 boxes)
  - Clippings (Box 84)
  - Clippings (Box 85)
    - Sarah and Francis W. Dawson I
    - Menus, invitations, and envelopes
  - Clippings (Box 86)
    - Williamsburg and Yorktown, Va.
  - Pamphlets (Box 87)
    - Joseph Conrad and Theodore Roosevelt
- Photographs Series, (4 boxes)
  - Revolutionary War (Box 88)
  - French soldiers
  - Williamsburg
  - Yorktown
  - Conrad, Joseph, family and Ellen (Box 89)
  - Theodore Roosevelt/Glasgow
  - Theodore Roosevelt's Expedition to Africa
  - Dawson family, relatives, etc. (Box 90)
  - Dawson friends (Box 91)
  - Miscellaneous
- French Manuscript Collection Series, (2 boxes)
  - List of the French manuscripts (Box 92)
  - Due de Sully, Bethune and Related Families, Folder I: 1-31
  - Due de Sully, Bethune and Related Families, Folders I: 32-41 (Box 93)
  - Miscellaneous, Folders II: 1-7
- 1998 Addition, 1850-1956, (6 boxes)